A Guide to the Matthew Fontaine Maury Papers, 1833-1873
Virginia Military Institute Archives
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
Matthew Fontaine Maury Papers 1833-1873
Archives, Preston Library, Virginia Military Institute
mss 00103
The collection consists of approximately 175 items.
The Matthew Fontaine Maury Papers consist largely of personal letters written by Maury to various members of his immediate family, 1840-1873.
Administrative Information
Access
There are no restrictions
Acquisition Information
The bulk of the collection was donated to the VMI Archives in 1989 by James Corbin.
Alternative Form
This collection is available in full-text format on the VMI Archives website at http://www.vmi.edu/archives.aspx?id=19209
Biographical/Historical Information
Matthew Fontaine Maury (b. 1806 d. 1873), naval officer and oceanographer known as the "Pathfinder of the Seas," was notable for his pioneering scientific work in the fields of navigation, hydrography, and meteorology. He joined the United States Navy at age 19 and in 1842 was named head of the Navy's hydrographical office and of the United State Naval Observatory. Beginning in the 1830's, he published a number of significant works on the Gulf Stream, ocean currents, and navigation, and was involved in research concerning deep-sea sounding and transoceanic cables.
A native of Virginia, Maury resigned his commission as Commander in the U. S. Navy at the outbreak of Civil War in April 1861. He entered the Confederate Navy and undertook research in the new technology of torpedo warfare; he was subsequently ordered to England as a special agent with instructions to purchase ships for the Confederate government. At war's end he was enroute to the United States with a cargo of torpedo equipment when, upon arriving in port at Havana, he learned that the war had ended. Maury then went to Mexico, where he served Emperor Maximilian, and later returned to England where he worked until 1868.
The last five years of Maury's life were spent as a Professor of Physics at the Virginia Military Institute in Lexington, Virginia. At VMI, Maury did not have regular classroom duties, but instead gave occasional lectures to the cadets and was primarily involved in overseeing an extensive physical survey of Virginia. He died in 1873.
Scope and Content Information
The Matthew Fontaine Maury Papers consist primarily of letters written by Maury to various members of his family, including daughter Diana Fontaine Maury Corbin, son-in-law Spotswood Wellford Corbin, and wife Ann Herndon Maury. Other correspondents include Maximilian, Emperor of Mexico, and Empress Carlotta. In addition to personal and domestic matters, topics include Maury's lecture series, his career at the National Observatory in Washington, D.C., Confederate service in Richmond, activities in England, colonization efforts in Mexico, and his professorship at the Virginia Military Institute. The papers also include misc. related correspondence, and printed material.
Contents List
- Correspondence, Family 1840-1872
  This correspondence series was given to VMI as a single donation by a descendant of Nannie Maury Corbin, a daughter of Matthew F. Maury.
  The abbreviation MFM is used in this finding aid to refer to Maury. Frequent correspondents include his wife Ann, his daughter Diana (Nannie) Maury Corbin, and son-in-law S. Wellford Corbin.
  - Letter 1840 November 10 (Box-folder 1/1)
    Place: Fredericksburg, VA; MFM to his mother, relating news of his children and other household news; presidential election.
  - Letter 1857 February 6 (Box-folder 1/2)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to S. Wellford Corbin, his daughter Diana's (Nannie) suitor. States that Nannie must wait one year before an engagement can take place.
  - Letter 1857 December 10 (Box-folder 1/3)
    Ferdinand Maximilian, Archduke of Austria to MFM; thanks Maury for sending a copy of Sailing Directions.
  - Letter 1857 December 10 (Box-folder 1/3)
  - Letter 1858 May 9 (Box-folder 1/4)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter Nannie, who has recently married Mr. Corbin. He provides advice for a happy marriage.
  - Letter 1858 May 31 (Box-folder 1/5)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter Nannie. Relates family news.
  - Letter 1858 August 15 (Box-folder 1/6)
    Place: White Sulphur, VA; MFM to his wife Ann Herndon Maury. Relates family news.
  - Letter 1858 September 12 (Box-folder 1/7)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter Nannie Corbin. Relates family news; will soon begin lecture series in Ohio and plans to use the money for son's schooling and to pay bills; will help to furnish Nannie's home (Farley Vale).
  - Letter 1858 October 3 (Box-folder 1/8)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter Nannie Corbin. Happy that Nannie is to visit; family news; is preparing grape vines and rose cuttings for her to take home to Farley Vale.
  - Letter 1858 November 18 (Box-folder 1/9)
    Place: Rochester, NY; MFM to wife, Ann. Lecture series is going well, large and attentive audience.
  - Letter 1858 November 20 (Box-folder 1/10)
    Place: Chicago, IL; MFM to wife, Ann. Relates itinerary for rest of lecture series; snowstorm in Chicago.
  - Letter 1858 November 23 (Box-folder 1/11)
    Place: Kalamazoo, Michigan; MFM to wife, Ann. Poor turnout at Chicago lecture due to weather; made only $50.
  - Letter 1858 November 27 (Box-folder 1/12)
    Place: Chicago, IL; MFM to wife, Ann. Talks generally about lecture series and distance he has traveled since leaving home.
  - Letter 1858 November 28 (Box-folder 1/13)
    Place: Chicago, IL; MFM to wife, Ann. Good audience at last lecture; leaving for Cincinnati.
  - Letter 1858 December 1 (Box-folder 1/14)
    Place: Cleveland, OH; MFM to daughter Nannie. Thanks her for writing her mother.
  - Letter 1858 December 1 (Box-folder 1/15)
    Place: Cleveland, OH; MFM to wife, Ann. Received letters; disruption in train schedule led to travel in a private car supplied by the president of the railroad.
  - Letter 1858 December 6 (Box-folder 1/16)
    Place: St. Louis, MO; MFM to wife, Ann. Movements for next week uncertain; going anywhere the most money can be made.
  - Letter 1859 February 17 (Box-folder 1/17)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter, Nannie. Sends Nannie the solution to a rebus (puzzle) enjoyed by the family.
  - Letter 1859 March 16 (Box-folder 1/18)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter, Nannie. Sending rose plants and vines; general family news.
  - Letter 1859 March 22 (Box-folder 1/19)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter, Nannie. Discusses loss in transit of plants sent to Corbins.
  - Letter 1859 March 22 (Box-folder 1/20)
  - Letter 1859 March 23 (Box-folder 1/21)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter, Nannie. Continuing discussion of loss in transit of plants sent to Corbins.
  - Letter 1859 April 12 (Box-folder 1/22)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to daughter, Nannie. General family news.
  - Letter 1859 April 14 (Box-folder 1/23)
  - Letter 1859 April 16 (Box-folder 1/24)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Alludes to legal matters regarding the management of the estate.
  - Letter 1859 April 19 (Box-folder 1/25)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his wife, Ann. Misses her; general family news.
  - Letter 1859 April 22 (Box-folder 1/26)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his daughter, Nannie Corbin. His ankle is injured and he has ordered crutches; talks of childrens' schools lessons; will send her plants.
  - Letter 1859 July 4 (Box-folder 1/27)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Discusses Nannie's desponding mood and asks Wellford to bring her to her mother for care.
  - Letter 1859 November 16 (Box-folder 1/28)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Discusses Corbin's legal matters; family news.
  - Letter 1860 February 5 (Box-folder 1/29)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his daughter, Nannie Corbin; postscript by Ann Maury. Family news.
  - Letter 1860 March 14 (Box-folder 1/30)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Regarding Corbin's legal matters.
  - Letter 1860 April 17 (Box-folder 1/31)
  - Letter 1860 May 12 (Box-folder 1/32)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his daughter, Nannie Corbin. Family news.
  - Letter 1860 July 9 (Box-folder 1/34)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his daughter, Nannie. Family news.
  - Letter 1860 August 6 (Box-folder 1/35)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC; MFM to his wife, Ann Herndon Maury. Family news.
  - Letter 1860 October 1 (Box-folder 1/36)
    Place: Naval Observatory, Washington, DC.
    MFM to his son-in-law, Wellford Corbin.
    Regarding signing a deed of trust upon the estate Farley Vale.
  - Letter 1860 October 2 (Box-folder 1/37)
    Regarding political situation in Virginia as it may affect property.
    ...it would be better for you Nannie and me if I had a lien also on your negro property as collateral for the land...
  - Letter 1860 November 21 (Box-folder 1/38)
    Place: London; MFM to his wife. Happy to receive letters; will return on the New York November 28.
  - Letter 1860 December 9 (Box-folder 1/39)
    Place: At Sea; MFM to his daughter, Nannie. Rough passage on his way home; describes stay in England; address before Geographical Society
  - Letter 1861 April 25 (Box-folder 1/40)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Outbreak of Civil War
    You can best serve the cause by staying at home, planting corn and potatoes...don't come.
  - Letter 1861 April 27 (Box-folder 1/41)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his wife. Family news.
  - Letter 1861 May 18 (Box-folder 1/42)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Explains plan to organize home guard:
    ...of all the remaining white population in the border and tidewater counties...to act in case of inroads and marauders as guerrillas...I think so highly of this plan that I have sought to have it turned over to us navy officers looking upon it as the most honorable and useful service that the times offer to us
    advises Corbin to consider this service... your whole fortune is imperiled, and it will require all the personal attention and the best management..to save you from ruin.
  - Letter 1861 June 20 (Box-folder 1/43)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Regarding Corbin's war service plans; failure of guerilla scheme.
  - Letter 1861 July 18 (Box-folder 1/44)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his wife. Discusses war news; troops at Norfolk
  - Letter 1861 September 18 (Box-folder 1/45)
    Place: Charlottesville, Virginia; MFM to his daughter, Nannie. Mentions Mr. Corbin's plans for service; looking for place to live, nothing suitable in Charlottesville
    waiting word to go ahead with submarines.
  - Letter 1861 November 20 (Box-folder 1/46)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his wife. General news.
  - Letter 1861 December 9 (Box-folder 1/47)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Corbin's leave is extended to Jan 1.
  - Letter 1861 December 9 (Box-folder 1/48)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his daughter, Nannie.
    Private and Confidential. Death of Milly a sad blow; Corbin may be able to get commission in Navy; looking for housing.
  - Letter 1862 January 30 (Box-folder 1/49)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to his wife. Family news; trying to get Corbin a commission.
  - Letter 1862 May 1 (Box-folder 1/50)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Regarding Dave's appointment.
  - Letter 1862 May 4 (Box-folder 1/51)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin.
    Your duties for the moment are and ought to be the all absorbing subjects with you...The enemy has the power to possess himself of Richmond - of the Miss. River and of all the Tidewater country. Look upon that as more than likely.
  - Letter 1862 May 5 (Box-folder 1/52)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Acknowledges receipt of letter.
  - Letter 1862 May 24 (Box-folder 1/53)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Family news.
  - Letter 1862 June 1 (Box-folder 1/54)
    Place: not given; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Dick slightly wounded in battle and will be out 6 weeks.
  - Letter 1862 June 5 (Box-folder 1/55)
    Jackson gives us a bright spot. In all the directions around the horizon the clouds lower upon us.
  - Letter 1862 June 19 (Box-folder 1/56)
    Place: not given; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Short note relaying family news.
  - Letter 1862 July 14 (Box-folder 1/57)
  - Letter 1862 July 19 (Box-folder 1/58)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Short note relaying family news.
  - Letter 1862 July 29 (Box-folder 1/59)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia, Exchange Hotel Room No. 12; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Short note relaying family news.
  - Letter 1862 July 30 (Box-folder 1/60)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia, Exchange Hotel Room No. 12; MFM to son-in-law, Lt. Wellford Corbin. Regarding situation in Fredericksburg (Pope's order to arrest those who will not swear allegiance).
  - Letter 1863 May 1 (Box-folder 1/61)
    Place: Bowdon, England; MFM to son-in-law, Wellford Corbin. Personal news; sees no end to war; Yankees trying to raise money in England.
  - Letter 1863 July 7 (Box-folder 1/62)
    Place: London, England; MFM to daughter, Nannie. Regarding trip to Paris; is depressed because of lack of progress:
    ...I am kept here all the time with hands tied for the want of means...told to build this and buy that as tho' I had the Bank of England to draw from.
  - Letter 1863 August 4 (Box-folder 1/63)
    Place: Bowdon, England; MFM to daughter Nannie. References to circumstances surrounding the death of his son John Herndon Maury (Davy), who died Jan. 1863.
  - Letter 1864 February 15 (Box-folder 1/64)
    Place: England; MFM to [?]. Family news
  - Letter 1864 March 4 (Box-folder 1/65)
    Place: England; MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Brief note.
  - Letter 1864 August 4 (Box-folder 1/66)
    Place: Bowdon, England; MFM to daughter, Nannie Corbin. Regarding capture of her husband
  - Letter 1864 December 30 (Box-folder 1/67)
    Place: The Parsonage, Belsize Park, London N.W., England; MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Short note.
  - Letter 1865 February 3 (Box-folder 1/68)
    Place: The Parsonage, Belsize Park, London N.W., England; MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Has been ill.
  - Letter 1865 May 19 (Box-folder 1/69)
    Place: At sea, off San Domingo; MFM to ? Discusses end of the war.
    ...I was utterly astounded at the brick-row tumble of our armies; and at the ignoble end of the Confederacy I am grieved and mortified beyond expression....The soil of Virginia has now for me no charms save those which memory flings around it....In my judgment the only course...that is left to those noble sons and daughters who have graced the fall of the noble old state is expatriation....And I go from Havana with the design of finding for them a new country....
  - Letter 1865 September 5 (Box-folder 1/70)
    Place: Mexico. Author: Emperor Maximilian (contemporary copy).
    Decree regarding immigration and benefits granted to immigrants; regulations regarding use of laborers
    ... Under the laws of the Empire, all persons of colour are free....
  - Letter 1865 September 5 (Box-folder 1/71)
    Place: Mexico. Author: Emperor Maximilian (MFM's copy). Additional regulations concerning immigration and colonization.
  - Letter 1865 September 11 (Box-folder 1/72)
    Place: Mexico. (MFM's copy of) Addendum to emperial decree, in which Maury outlines the climate, economy and other features of Mexico for the information of prospective immigrants.
  - Letter 1865 October 31 (Box-folder 1/73)
    Place: Office of Colonization, 13 Calle San Juan de Letran, Mexico. MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin. Comments about colonization effort and false rumors that he has requested a pardon from the U. S. government.
  - Letter 1865 October 31 (Box-folder 1/74)
    Place: Office of Colonization, 13 Calle San Juan de Letran, Mexico. MFM to son-in-law Wellford Corbin; copy by Rutson Maury, with notations. Identical content to above item (folder 73).
  - Letter 1865 November 27 (Box-folder 1/75)
    Place: Office of Colonization, Mexico. MFM to his wife, Ann. References to going to England; situation in Virginia; colonization.
  - Letter 1865 November 30 (Box-folder 1/76)
    Mexico. MFM to his daughter, Nannie. Urges her and Corbin to consider establishing a settlement in Mexico.
  - Letter 1865 December 7 (Box-folder 1/77)
    Mexico. MFM to his daughter, Nannie. Further discussion possibility of Nannie and husband settling in Mexico.
  - Letter 1865 December 9 (Box-folder 1/78)
    Place: Mexico. Document announcing offer to Confederate settlers to purchase the estate of Santa Anna.
  - Letter 1865 December 10 (Box-folder 1/79)
    Place: Colonization Office, Mexico. Document concerning offer to Confederate settlers to purchase the estate of Santa Anna.
    The Hacienda offered herewith known to have been one of the finest and most celebrated in Mexico. It presents, especially to the former planters of the South, a fine opportunity for establishing a flourishing American settlement.
  - Letter 1865 December 10 (Box-folder 1/79)
    Place: Colonization Office, Mexico.
  - Letter 1865 December (Box-folder 1/80)
    Letter fragment in hand of Richard Maury.
    Va. is not a fit place to live in now. All must come to Mexico....
  - Letter 1865 December (Box-folder 1/81)
    Letter fragment, copied by Nannie Corbin. Regarding colonization.
  - Letter 1866 January 1 (Box-folder 2/1)
    Place: Mexico. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Continuing discussion of Corbin's possible settlement in Mexico.
    It will be more consistent with your self respect to abandon that country at least for the present. Don't stay there and help fasten the yoke upon y'r own neck that my precious Davy Jones gave up his life in trying to shake off....
  - Letter 1866 January 18 (Box-folder 2/2)
    Place: Mexico. Copy of letter from MFM to Empress Charlotte (Carlotta) regarding colonization and internal improvements.
  - Letter 1866 January 29 (Box-folder 2/3)
    Place: Cuernavaca, Mexico.
    Copy of letter from Emperor Maximilian to MFM, regarding his family's settlement in Mexico. In Spanish.
  - Letter 1866 January 29 (Box-folder 2/4)
    Copy of letter from Empress Charlotte (Carlotta) to MFM, regarding his leave of absence in England.
  - Letter 1866 February 2 (Box-folder 2/5)
    Place: Mexico. MFM to children.
    Is leaving for England; colonization going forward with various settlement.
  - Letter 1866 March 1 (Box-folder 2/6)
    Describes his stage and rail journey across Mexico to seaport; discusses ongoing colonization in Mexico and political situation in Virginia.
  - Letter 1866 May 21 (Box-folder 2/7)
    Place: Paris, France. MFM to Wellford Corbin.
    Problems back in Mexico with regard to colonization.
    Now I tell you and Nannie confidentially, that what has happened since I left Mexico has shaken my resolution about going back.
  - Letter 1866 August 11 (Box-folder 2/8)
    Place: England.
    MFM to Wellford Corbin.
    Has decided not to return to Mexico; discussion of Corbin's legal affairs with regard to Farley Vale estate
  - Letter 1866 December 9 (Box-folder 2/9)
    Place: 3 Belsize Square, London, England.
    MFM to Nannie.
    Family news; references to the Corbins' financial and legal affairs.
  - Letter 1867 May 19 (Box-folder 2/10)
    Approves of his decision to abandon the rebuilding of Farley Vale; pessimistic about future of the South--extensive discussion of his views.
  - Letter 1867 September 22 (Box-folder 2/11)
    Mentions possible business opportunity for Corbin; family news.
  - Letter 1868 January 29 (Box-folder 2/12)
    Mentions renting of Farley Vale
  - Letter 1868 January 29 (Box-folder 2/12)
    Place: 3 Belsize Square, London, England MFM to Wellford Corbin. Mentions renting of Farley Vale
  - Letter 1868 February 8 (Box-folder 2/13)
    Regarding Corbins' future plans and possibility of Maury taking position at University of the South in Tennessee.
  - Letter 1868 April 15 (Box-folder 2/14)
    Family news.
  - Letter 1868 April 25 (Box-folder 2/15)
    Family news; illness of baby.
  - Letter 1868 May 13 (Box-folder 2/16)
    Family news; baby is better; plans to help revive industry in Virginia with steam agricultural machinery.
  - Letter 1868 July 2 (Box-folder 2/17)
    Place: Liverpool, England MFM to Wellford Corbin. Family is ready to embark on trip home.
  - Letter 1868 July 2 (Box-folder 2/18)
    Place: Liverpool, England MFM to Wellford Corbin, with note by Rutson Maury dated 13 July. Regarding family luggage; note by R. Maury reports weather at sea.
  - Letter 1868 August 3 (Box-folder 2/19)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Regarding legal matters.
  - Letter 1868 August 8 (Box-folder 2/20)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to daughter Nannie. Fragment.
  - Letter 1868 September 4 (Box-folder 2/21)
    Place: Rockbridge Baths, Virginia. MFM to daughter Nannie. Family news; VMI Superintendent Francis H. Smith will come tomorrow to take him to Lexington, where he will be officially installed on the faculty of the Virginia Military Institute. Will then return to Rockbridge Baths and then on to Richmond. I go to work immediately in preparing a preliminary report of the natural wealth and c. of Va. such as its climates, productions and favored position.
  - Letter 1868 September 22 (Box-folder 2/22)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Short note containing family news; mention of Corbin's court case; wants Corbin to send him average prices of wheat, corn etc.
  - Letter 1868 October 4 (Box-folder 2/23)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Thanking him for statistics regarding grain prices; family news.
  - Letter 1868 October 11 (Box-folder 2/24)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Family news.
  - Letter 1868 December 3 (Box-folder 2/25)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Regarding insolvency of Corbin's tenant; family news.
  - Letter 1868 December 11 (Box-folder 2/26)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Regarding insolvency of Corbin's tenant and resulting problems.
  - Letter 1868 December 23 (Box-folder 2/27)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Regarding insolvency of Corbin's tenant and resulting problems; Christmas greetings.
  - Letter 1869 January 8 (Box-folder 2/28)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Mentions Corbin's business problems; family news.
  - Letter 1869 January 14 (Box-folder 2/29)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Mentions Corbin's business problems; discusses publication of his report on the Physical Survey of Virginia.
  - Letter 1869 January 29 (Box-folder 2/30)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. References to publication of his report on the Physical Survey of Virginia.
  - Letter 1869 February 1 (Box-folder 2/31)
    Place: Richmond, Virginia. MFM to Wellford Corbin. Additional discussion of the publication of his Physical Survey of Virginia.
  - Letter 1869 February 16 (Box-folder 2/32)